Rhiannon: Psychotherapy, talking
therapy, counselling, or simply
therapy, are some of the terms used
as alternatives to medication and
can really benefit people struggling
with emotional difficulties, life
challenges, and mental health concerns.
Medication can reduce some of the
symptoms of mental health conditions,
but therapy teaches people skills to
address symptoms on their own, and
these can stay with the individual after
therapy ends, and as symptoms improve,
the need for treatment may reduce.
Untreated mental health issues often
get worse and may have other negative
effects affecting work, study,
relationships and general health.
A therapist can give support
going forward, and once a crisis
is over, they can be a safe
haven for when things get tough.
Psychological therapies services are
also known as Improving Access to
Psychological Therapies [IAPT] services.
Examples of these are, talking therapies
like counselling for depression, and
cognitive behavioural therapy [CBT]
and are available on the NHS with
referral from a GP or self-referral.
There are many different types of
‘talking therapy’, but they all involve
working with a trained therapist.
The therapist helps find answers
to the problems the child
or young person is having.
One type of talking therapy may be
better than another, and different
talking therapies suit different people.